<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bioactive Glasses | Achraf Atila</title>
    <link>https://Atilaac.github.io/tag/bioactive-glasses/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://Atilaac.github.io/tag/bioactive-glasses/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Bioactive Glasses</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Achraf Atila</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 16:48:07 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://Atilaac.github.io/images/icon_hu1596d6b584804863b1721867b7828bbf_230556_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Bioactive Glasses</title>
      <link>https://Atilaac.github.io/tag/bioactive-glasses/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bioactive Glasses</title>
      <link>https://Atilaac.github.io/project/bioactive-glasses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 16:48:07 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Atilaac.github.io/project/bioactive-glasses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bioactive glasses have potential applications in the field of regenerative medicine due to their bioactivity, which enables the interactions with both hard and soft tissues. The soda-lime phosphosilicate glasses, such as 45S5, represent a model system of bioactive glasses. Regardless of their importance as bioactive materials, the relationship between the structure, pressure, and cooling process was not studied in detail. This affects the progress of further development of bioactive glasses negatively.  Our contribution to the field of bioactive glasses is to tailor/ enhance the mechanical properties of bioactive glasses. We used molecular dynamics simulations to study the dynamical, elastic, and structural properties of densified 45S5 bioactive glass over a large range of densities. We performed a systematic analysis of the glass structure to density in order correlate the change in the properties to the structural change with a target to enhance the mechanical elasticity of the bioactive glasses while keeping their bioactive nature. The results show that the glass structure tends to be repolymerized as indicated by an increase of the network connectivity. This, was accompanied by a tetrahedral to octahedral polyhedral transformation. We were able to tailor the elastic properties while keeping the bioactivity of the glass. This to the best of our knowledge the first study to address the improvement of the elastic/ mechanical properties of bioactive glasses through densification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results obtained in these studies will allow us to enhance the mechanical properties of bioactive glasses and opens a new window for further development and optimization of the bioglasses properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More studies are to be published soon, stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
